Monroe Papers, Ashlawn, 1795-1834 and n.d.
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Monroe Papers, Ashlawn 1795-1834 and n.d.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. Acc. 2003.9
This collection consists of 28 items.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by "Ash Lawn," 2003 February 13.
Biographical/Historical Information
See Harry Ammon, James Monroe: the Quest for National Identity and W. P. Cresson, James Monroe.
Mme. Campan was a former lady-in-waiting to Marie Antoinette. She ran the most fashionable school in France and her niece married General Ney (Marshal Ney).
Hortense de Beauharnais was born in Paris in 1783, died in Switzerland in 1837. She was the daughter of Alexandre de Beauharnais and Josephine Tascher de la Pagerie (empress Josephine, wife of Napoleon). She married Louis, Napoleon I's brother who became king of Holland. She was sent into exile during the second Restoration. Her son was Emperor Napoleon III.
George Hay (1765-1830)
Eliza Kortright Monroe Hay (1787-1840)
Hortensia Monroe Hay Rogers (1809?-1854), granddaughter of James Monroe
Tench Ringgold (1776-1844)
Egbert Read Watson (1810- 1887)
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1795-1834 and n.d., of Eliza Kortright Monroe Hay. Includes letters written by and to her and to her father James Monroe. Correspondents include her former teacher Madame [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan, her daughter Hortensia M. Rogers of "Druid Hill" near Baltimore, Md., her son-in-law Lloyd N. Rogers as well as the daughter of Marquis de Lafayette, Marie Antoinette Virginie de Lafayette Lasteyrie du Saillant. Subjects include the debts and final illness of James Monroe, the final illness of George Hay, the possible sale by the Hay family of "Ashfield," [near Richmond, Va.], the aftermath of the French Revolution, Hortense de Beauharnais (the stepdaughter of Napoleon and the mother of Napoleon III), Samuel L. Gouverneur and his wife Maria Hester Monroe Gouverneur, Tench Ringgold and Egbert Read Watson.
Contents List
- 10 January 1795 ( 20 Niv^se 3) [dated from the founding of the Republic]), 2 pages on one leaf. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English (Folder 1)
  Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to James Monroe. I have received last summer a letter which had come under cover of your address and which you had sent to me by Mr. [?] formerly Charges des affairs of Portugal and who now resides in this town. He wrote several times in answer to Monsieur D'Arago at the Hague. Eliza is marvelously well. They are preparing a play.
- 9 October 1803, Madame [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan, St Germaine [France] to E[liza]; K[ortright]; M[onroe] Hay. 3 pages on one leaf. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English. (Folder 2)
  Takes advantage of departure of General McPherson to answer you and to tell you that I am infinitely touched by your kind remembrance. I can not console myself for your departure and that of your dear Parent. Madame Garnot has just been dangerously ill. M. Auguie was losing his mind from despair. You know how interesting Mde Garnot was both through her virtues and her talents. Madame Ney is still in Berne with the general. She is pregnant with her second child. Madame Lambert also will give us a little nephew in two or three months. Your old comrade Hortense [de Beauharnais] is with her husband... News of other female friends. Lucy Crabtree was not able to profit by the opportunity afforded by General McPherson, the expenses of travel seemed too high for her. Thank your dear Papa for letters which contained bills of exchange. Imagine how your good father must be full of thoughts for his two little girls who are here.
- 17 Jan. 1804, Mme. [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to Eliza Monroe. 4 pages on one leaf. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English. (Folder 3)
  "Charming little savage" who has seen the world... I greet you for the New Year. Charged bearer to kiss you both for me. He is a father of a family... once very rich, today without fortune - but superior to reverses thorough his courage and his virtues. We have his daughter... interesting Nellie Bour-jolli of the blue class. Before long you will see Lucy Crabtree. Miss Lucy will bring you the Dialogues which I have had printed and which will be very useful for French and Italian." Asks for English books. Received letter of 12 pages from brother. General [?] and his wife have returned from Switzerland. Madame Hortense is at [?] with her husband. It is a town in Picardie. Husband of Hortense is there at the head of his regiment.
- 1 May 1816, Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to M[onsieur James] Monroe, Sec. of State. 3 pages on one leaf. In English. Halton loan. (Folder 4)
  Misfortunes of this revolution. Retired to a little town 15 leagues from Paris and enjoying son's society. Lost three thousand pounds. Battle near farm. So deprived of farm's rent. Nerves of stomach. Recall myself to you, my dear Madame Monroe and my dear scholar Eliza. Only sends letters of recommendation for a few people. Eliza has been indisposed at pains in part of her body after her lying ill. Wearing of flannel shifts and our waters in France, were the proper remedy. Must have some waters on new continent which bear some analogy with Barrage's waters.
- 27 May 1819, Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan, Nantes [France] to M[onsieur James] Monroe. 2 pages on one leaf. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English. (Folder 5)
  I have been moved to tears on receiving a new proof of friendship granted by my dear pupil Mrs. Hay. Your good president and the so kind Mrs. Monroe. I shall write to the ambassador and to Madame Ney. I also dare to pray you to have the enclosed letter sent to Monsieur le Chevalier de Mun.
- 30 October 1821, Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 3 pages on one leaf. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English. (Folder 6)
  I am exceedingly anxious about everything concerning you and your respected parents. The loss of my dear husband. A painful gland in my breast gives me just fears, concerning the duration of my existence. My poor son was very tenderly touched by the interest you had taken in his sad destinies. I have seen Hortense [de Beauharnais] in her country house. She has recovered her health. She goes over her very little domain and is busy beautifying it. You know how much I cherished her when she was a Republican citizen having lost her passing crown.
- 1 Sept. 1829., Eliza K[ortright]; M[onroe] Hay, "Oak Hill" to son-in-law Lloyd N. Rogers. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 7)
  Their trip. Entirely laid to rest anxieties regarding her health. Mr. Hay [George Hay]suffered with vertigo. My father (James Monroe) wrote you for Hortensia to bring the children. I am half cracked to see Eleanor.
- 17 January 1830, Hortensia M. Rogers to mother Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 8)
  Rejection of grandfather's claim. Knew it would be rejected if Fenton Mercer introduced bill. Servants sick with measles.
- 8 April 1830, E[liza]; K[ortright]; M[onroe] Hay to son-in-law Lloyd N. Rogers. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 9)
  Your letter shows you are under the influence of a great misapprehension as to the cause and course of my feelings as indicated in my letters to Hortensia. Husband's health has been very delicate. Go to Washington to see Dr. Hunt. I certainly will come to my child, my only child and as you say, "at a moment when she will most require the care of her Mother." Uncertain of the date when she should come.
- 16 September 1830, Hortensia M. Rogers to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 10)
  Illness of George Hay and Mrs. James Monroe. Lloyd Rogers back from funeral of Harry Rogers. Won't come because afraid to bring baby.
- 12 December 1830, H[ortensia]; M[onroe](Hay) Rogers to mother Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 1 page. (Folder 11)
  Received two copies of Sam's oration. Lloyd spitting blood. The 11th was day appointed for sale. Some delighted to hear grandpapa is so much better.
- 28 December 1830., Hortensia Monroe Rogers to mother Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 2 pages. (Folder 12)
  Mr. Rogers is much better. Bled five times. I am extremely sorry to hear that "Ashfield" was not sold. I would hire out and sell all the blacks I could. Glad to hear that a movement has been made in New York as to my grandfather's claims. Ask Maria Gouverneur why she does not write to me.
- 4 Jany. 1831., Hortensia M. Rogers to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 13)
  Mr. Rogers looks badly. All the servants have the measles. Sorry to read accounts of 1 of January dinners. He [James Monroe] is very old and recent misfortune demands seclusion not solitude. If he sees company it should be of a different sort from Morris, Livingston, Ogden. Grandfather's claim has been brought forward by Fenton Mercer. Doesn't like Thomas Swann visiting. Tell me something of Maria Gouverneur. I do not wish to interfere in Aunt M's concerns. She has a husband to take care of her.
- February 1, 1831, H[ortensia]; M[onroe]; R[ogers]"Druid Hill" [near Baltimore Md.] to mother Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 4 pages on one leaf. (Folder 14)
  Concerned at accounts of grandpapa's health. His sleepiness. Sends bundle. Sent to Skinner to ask him to give it to Sam. Mr. Rogers wearing cotton wadding next to breast. Recovering usual health. Needs some socks of lamb's wool. Mrs. West is knitting the baby some but that is a slow process. Enclose a few lines from a letter from Mary Mercer which is all I have heard of the claim. Has pattern for cape to be worn entirely in the street. Baby has beautiful skin. I forgot to mention that both Frank and Fanny will be free if they stay here 6 months.
- 6 February 1831, Hortensia M[onroe]; R[ogers]"Druid Hill" [near Baltimore Md.] to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. Received letter from Sam[uel L. Gouverneur]. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 15)
  Papers announced passage of bill for $30,000 (for James Monroe). Senate may increase it. John Mercer says abuse was gross and Sam says he was insulted on the floor of the Senate himself. She (Antoinette) told me you had written to her telling her of the offer for "Ash Field" - that she had sold all the Ashfield negroes for 1400 dollars.
- 4 March 1831, H. M. R (Hortensia M. Rogers) to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay, New York. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 16)
  Mr. Rogers has been sent for to go to his sister whom he scarcely expects to find alive. He will give you a minute account of the baby who without vanity is a sweet looking baby. Letter from Sam saying he would take a meal with us en passant. It was written the minute the claim passed. I fear you trouble yourself about making things for the baby. I have Mr. Rogers' things to pack. Have had no spirit. Languid. Have not strength to nurse the baby in warm weather. Will take calomel when I have weaned her. Give my love to Louisa and thank her for the little necklace would like to see her. Mrs. Murray is better.
- 26 March 1831, Hortensia M. Rogers, "Druid Hill" [near Baltimore Md.]," to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay, New York. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 17)
  Upset at her last letter. Delighted with things for baby. Not ill-crossed brat. My grandfather would not be able to sell "Oak Hill." I hear "Ash Field" was not sold. Egbert Watson is still here. Shall be sorry to see all the negroes sold. So do not propose to me to take them for in the first place I would only buy them in. If I took them at all as any other bidder.
- 4 May 1831, Hortensia M. Rogers, "Druid Hill" [near Baltimore Md.]," to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 18)
  I do not feel alarmed for grandfather. Would go to New York directly but cannot see that I could be of any use to him. Bring Monroe to her house but recommends they consult Dr. Physic in Philadelphia. Thought she had scarlet fever. I shall begin today to wean my baby. I cannot suckle her any longer. I have not strength.
- 17 May 1831, (H. M. Rogers) Hortensia to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 3 pages on one leaf. (Folder 19)
  Hope grandfather continues to gain strength. He is head of our family, the cornerstone of our building. Educated her. Upset that James Monroe (probably nephew) is coolly calculating on his death. Has gotten Life of Byron. Hear Byron is very indelicate. Not fit for ladies to hear. You parted from me in anger. I hardly know why. Couldn't carry a child into disease. Did you not carry me to my poor grandmother's to avoid the measles.
- 1831 June 27, (H. M. Rogers) Hortensia to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 1 page. (Folder 20)
  Can't come. Child continuously sick. Will come if she thinks grandfather (James Monroe) would even know her - Sam's letter precludes all hope. Wants grandfather's blessing, I never had my father's [deathbed blessing?]
- October 1831, Hortensia M. Rogers to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 21)
  Occupied with baby and sick servants. Treating servants. Are to have a convention in Baltimore to pick presidential candidate. Lanced my baby's gums. Describes quilt she is working on. I could not learn much about my old friend from him. Mary Custis or Lee is at Point Comfort.
- 4 June 1834, Clemence Partiot to Madame Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 22)
  I hope you have received the [?] I sent you yesterday. Let me offer you today a very little token of my attachment to you. A little dog the emblem of my [?] and fidelity in what I promised you then a silver medal which has been made for my poor aunt Campan and which you will perhaps find precious for her sake and lastly a little French theater fan which belonged to my poor mother. I embrace you in the French way "de tout mon coeur." God bless you and give you a happy passage.
- n.d., G. C. [Mme. Jeanne Campan] to James Monroe. In English. Halton loan 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 23)
  Needs to sell two beautiful editions of the most curious kind, only remains of a very fine library I once possessed. If you know among the Americans some body who could desire to purchase them you'll oblige me sincerely. Eliza is in very good health and I hope in a few months that she will be generally improved.
- n.d., Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to Pres. Monroe. 2 pages on one leaf. In English. Halton loan. (Folder 24)
  Sorry they can't visit and that the cause is friend's illness. Has he seen M. [Sabatier ?] the celebrated surgeon in Paris. I intended to procure very pleasant walks to Mrs. Monroe to lead her to a party of [?] which may be she never saw before. Hope she will come and Mr. [?] will be soon better. I send you my receipt of the two [?] Eliza works prettily. She cried the first day she came back saying she had lost of her writing since her absence from school. Her [?] is her only defect.
- n.d., Genet [Jeanne Louise Henriette] Campan to pupil. 1 p. In French but includes English translation. Abstract is done from English. (Folder 25)
  I have experienced great misfortunes and my health suffered from it. I send you some printing matters which will interest you. They are a noble defense in my favor for the outrages which the pamphleteers have made me suffer so unjustly.
- n.d., Pavis Y Ventose to Eliza Monroe. May be schoolmate of Eliza Monroe. 3 pages on one leaf. In French. Halton loan. (Folder 26)
  [*Vent^se is the name of one of the French republic months.]
- n.d., Marie Antoinette Virginie de] Lafayette Lasteyrie [du Saillant] to Madame Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 27)
  In French. Concerns her father [Marquis de Lafayette].
- n.y. October 15., Hortensia Monroe Rogers to Mrs. [Eliza Kortright Monroe] Hay. 2 pages on one leaf. (Folder 28)
  Put off writing. Expecting to see Cousin Sam[uel L. Gouverneur]. Worried about health of child. Thinks Papa will like his room. Ice house had caved in. Tench [Ringgold] told me grandpapa intended to stay some day with him.